For this episode, I decided to break from my usual routine.
这一期我突然打破了常规的惯例啊
I want to talk about Elon Musk.
我想讲一讲马斯克啊
I'll keep it relatively short.
呃我会把讲的稍微的短一点
To help improve the completion rate for viewers.
方便大家提高完播率
That's the plan.
是这样
I think Marxke's reforms may not necessarily succeed.
我认为马克思克的改革呢会不一定会成功啊
They might fail midway.
他可能会中道崩图
There could be a significant issue.
可能会呃出现一个很大的问题
Such as a potential threat to personal safety.
就是可能人身安全会有问题啊
This is my personal judgment
这个是我的个人判断
But it's not necessarily about personal safety; it might reach a point where
但未必是人身安全可能到一定程度以后呃
sacrificing a pawn to save the game becomes necessary.
弃卒保驹啊
Stepping down to a secondary role,
这个退居二线呐
or even resigning altogether.
卸任呐
And then moving overseas
然后移居海外啊
It's all possible
都有可能呃
From a historical perspective
从历史的角度来讲的话
Such measures to reduce the power of feudal lords
像这种削藩啊
Reforms by Shang Yang
搞改革商鞅
Wang Anshi
王安石
Chao Cuo
晁错啊
Zhang Juzheng, their outcomes weren't particularly good
张居正下场都不是特别的好啊
Now, as you know, Jia Xu is very popular I am in sync with Jia Xu's heart. Jia Xu's principle in life is to deceive and harm others. He harms the nobles,
呃大家知道现在贾诩非常的这个流行 我是跟贾诩心连心的 贾诩的一个人的做人的原则呢 就是他坑人害人 他害贵族
but he also aligns himself with them.
但是他同时也站对贵族啊
After he exhausts the nobles,
他把贵族消耗了以后呢
it is actually the people who benefit.
实际上是人民得意
But no matter which noble family,
但是无论哪家贵族
he doesn’t hesitate to lead Li Jue and Guo Si to kill the nobles in Chang'an.
他不管是引这个李觉郭嗣去杀长安的贵族
Still, he uses Zhang Xiu to kill Cao Cao
还是引用张绣去杀曹操
or uses Cao Cao to eliminate others
还是引用曹操去杀其他人
in reality, it’s all about reducing the number of nobles
实际都在消耗贵族的数量
because he understands that as the number of nobles decreases
因为他明白贵族的数量下降了
the safety of the people is secured
人民的安全就保障了
just like in Game of Thrones
就像权力的游戏
it’s because there are too many nobles
就是因为贵族太多
that so many people are recruited to fight wars
所以才有那么多人征兵去打仗
so he sticks to this principle
所以他是保持这个原则
But if your reform approach is from the bottom up,
但是如果你的改革方式是自下而上的
you stand on the side of the people,
是你站在人民一头啊
you will be remembered in history,
你是会青史留名
but you will certainly not meet a good end,
但是一定会不得好死
ending up like Yu Qian,
结果就是像于谦那样
facing the same fate,
也是这样
that’s you,
就是你啊
because the people, when they rise up to kill, lack the power,
因为人民他一头杀是没有力量的
those people in those countries The power is diluted suppressed at the grassroots level he lacks substantial support and the political struggles among the nobility have been going on since ancient times when you attempt reforms or initiatives like these you're essentially infringing on the nobles' interests
他的那些国家的那些人啊 力量被分散 被压制在基层 他是没有实际支持的力量 而这个自古以来党争贵族之争 你搞改革 搞这些东西 实际上都是侵犯贵族利益
whether it's the pharmaceutical conglomerate
不管是这个制药集团啊
the Silicon Valley group, or the military-industrial complex
硅谷集团还是这个军备集团
How do you say these?
这些怎么说呢
These financial conglomerates
这些金融集团
In the U.S., they are a few major ones
这美国他是几个大型的
These people, they just keep doing the same old thing
这些人他是不换换汤不换药
I rarely do it on a regular basis
就是我平时很少做
Now I seldom produce content about the U.S.
现在我很少做关于美国的内容
It's because, as you all know, my viewpoint is
就是因为啊你大家知道我的观点是
Both China and the U.S. are great nations
中美两国都是非常伟大的国家
I usually don't comment on America's domestic affairs
一般我不怎么评论美国的内政
But this time, I really feel it's a pity for this person.
但是这次我觉得真的是这个人挺可惜的
Because relying on the people to push for reform
因为背靠人民去搞改革
usually ends up being very tragic.
通常的结果就是会非常惨
He would end up very tragically as well.
他是这样会非常惨啊
Trump used him to say
川普利用他来讲
at a critical moment, he wore a glove.
关键时刻他戴一个手套
You could discard this glove.
你可以弃用这个手套
Or spread rumors of discord between the two or something.
或者传出两人不和或者怎么样
This issue can ultimately be smoothed over.
这个问题最终都能下得来台
But people like royal envoys or such
但像这种国王密使或者这种啊
This one wearing the yellow jacket bearing the imperial sword usually don't end up with a particularly good outcome because if he doesn't leave the United States after four years the outcome might not be particularly good because he is an entrepreneur with a pure heart
这个披着黄马褂 带着尚方宝剑的人 通常最后的结果都不会特别好啊 因为如果他4年之后他不离开美国的话 可能结果就不会特别好 因为他是一个有赤子之心的一个企业家
who really works with incredible efficiency
他做事情真的是非常有效率
and has offended the clan groups
得罪了氏族集团
He offended the aristocratic group
得罪了贵族集团啊
He has an interest group
他有利益集团
an interest group, to put it that way
interest group这样来讲
which makes the ultimate issue hard to resolve
到最终的问题就是很难解决
Because historically speaking
因为在历史上来讲
remember, you can only rely on one faction of the nobility to suppress
你记住就是你只能靠一派贵族去积压啊
the other faction of the nobility
打压另外一派贵族啊
You can't rely on the New Aristocracy to eliminate the aristocrats.
你能靠着新贵族就消灭旧贵族
and rely on nobles from different regions to gain the upper hand
能靠着不同地方的贵族去占据这个上风啊
But you can't completely rely on Vero, can you?
但是你不可能说完完全全不依靠维鲁啊
Then lay off 97% of the department?
然后把97%的这个部门全部裁撤掉
You have to understand, these people are not just their positions,
你要知道这些人他不光是他的职位啊
but they have disciples and former colleagues all over the place.
而且是他门生故吏遍天下
They form a vast network of connections.
他是一个庞大的关系网啊
Close relatives and close friends,
三亲的俩热的
so these interest groups are not something to be easily tampered with.
所以这些利益集团的这个东西
They are not usually very easy to move around. Unless you can break them down into several pieces. There's something new to replace him To sum it up Just like Caesar in Rome He ultimately died from the daggers of many, including Brutus
都不是通常特别好动的 除非你能把它拆分成好几块 有新的东西来替代他 总之来讲的话 就像罗马的凯撒一样 最终死在了布鲁图斯的那么多人的小刀之下
He might end up with the same fate
他有可能最终就是一样的结果
So, in this context
所以这个东西来讲
A reform that burns all bridges
破釜沉舟式的改革
Usually turns out to be incomplete
通常来讲的话就是他是不彻底的
And it relies on administrative measures
而且他是利用行政手段去做这些东西的
He wasn't about a bottom-up transformation of the class system
他不是自下而上的这种变阶级
a thorough revolution that would change the relationships completely
变关系的彻底的革命来讲的话
In practice, the results would be hard to sustain
实际上来讲效果最终很难保持
Moreover, his personal safety would be at risk
然后他个人安全很难去那什么
And at the same time, he would make too many enemies
而且同时树敌太多啊
That's usually not a good thing
通常不是什么好事啊
Looking at Chinese history
从中国的历史上来讲
Those who understood how to manage the aristocratic groups
凡是能把贵族集团玩明白的人
Could all become emperors and achieve great things
都能啊称帝都能做成一番伟业
Could all successfully usurp the throne
都能篡位成功
But those who never took the aristocratic groups seriously
但是从来不把贵族集团放在眼里的人
And only cared about the interests of the common people
只把人民老百姓的利益放在眼里的人
Usually ended up as tragic heroes
通常到最后都是悲剧英雄
We really shouldn't follow in Musk's footsteps
真的是不能学马斯克啊
From an idealistic standpoint
然后理想主义上来讲的话
I think it might make one famous in history But it also makes one very likely to meet a bad end
我觉得虽然容易青史留名 但极容易不得好死